Guide to the School of Engineering, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
School of Engineering, Yale University, records
1910-1987
RU 447
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13.75
The records consist of correspondence, subject and personnel files, memoranda, curriculum and program materials, student grades, research papers, and field trip reports documenting the administrative operations and activities of the Yale School of Engineering.
Yale University. School of Engineering
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 23-A (YRG 23-A), Central records and records of the dean of the Yale School of Engineering.
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Arrangement
The records are arranged as follows: I. General records of the School of Engineering, 1910-1964. II. Electrical Engineering Department, 1911-1958. III. Mechanical Engineering Department, 1921-1964. IV. Transportation Department, 1920-1948; and in subsequent accessions.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, subject and personnel files, curriculum and program materials, student grades, research papers, and field trip reports documenting the administrative operations and activities of the Yale School of Engineering.
Biographical / Historical
Applied science and engineering instruction at Yale began in the year 1846 with the establishment of Agricultural Chemistry and Applied Chemistry professorships by the Yale Corporation. The following year, 1847, this "School of Applied Chemistry" was included within the newly created Department of Philosophy and the Arts. In 1852 a School of Engineering was instituted with the approval of a civil engineering professorship. Science and engineering courses were independent, but listed together in the catalogue "under the aegis of a non-existent institution" known as the Yale Scientific School. Efforts were made in 1856 to formally organize a school of science; a proposed plan was drawn up and fund raising pamphlets issued. The generous donations of funds and property by Joseph Earl Sheffield in 1858 made possible the official establishment of the Yale Scientific School, in which chemistry and engineering courses were offered. In recognition of Sheffield's continued patronage, the Yale Scientific School was renamed the Sheffield Scientific School (SSS) in 1861. The SSS experienced numerous academic and physical changes during the years that followed. In 1932 the School of Engineering was re-established and SSS engineering courses transferred to the new school. The SSS began to function at the graduate level only in 1945 when undergraduate courses for the Bachelor of Science degree were transferred to Yale College. SSS was terminated in 1956, and its faculty moved to the Division of Science to teach graduate courses. In 1961 a separate Engineering and Applied Science Department was established. This department was reorganized in 1981 into the Council of Engineering, which consisted of the Department of Chemical Engineering and three engineering sections: applied physics, electrical, and applied mechanics. The council became the Departments of Chemical, Electrical, and Mechanical Engineering along with one section of applied physics in 1983. The Department of Biomedical Engineering was created in 2003. In 2008 the department became the School of Engineering and Applied Science. In 2010 the Department of Mechanical Engineering was renamed the Department of Mechanical Engineering and Materials Science, the Department of Chemical Engineering was renamed the Department of Chemical and Environmental Engineering, and Applied Physics became a department in the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences. In 2015 the Department of Computer Science became part of the School of Engineering and Applied Science.
Electrical engineering -- Study and teaching; Engineering -- Study and teaching; Mechanical engineering -- Study and teaching; Transportation -- Study and teaching; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Departments; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. School of Engineering
- Records, 1910-1964; Accession 1965-A-001
  Conditions Governing Access
  Student records in boxes 11-13 are restricted until January 1, 2033 and Faculty working sheets in boxes 22-23 are restricted until January 1, 2034 as established by Yale Corporation regulations..
  Scope and Contents
  The School of Engineering Records contain historical information on applied science and engineering instruction at Yale spanning the years 1910 to 1964. The papers are divided into four series: General Records, Electrical Engineering Department, Mechanical Engineering Department, and Transportation Department. Included in these papers is information on the reorganization of engineering instruction, class excercises, student grades, field trips, new buildings and equipment for the departments, and federally funded research. The papers may be of use to researchers interested in the formation and development of engineering instruction at Yale.
  Separated Materials
  Four linear feet of material were removed from these records. They are now in MS 779, Charles Felton Scott Papers, as Accession 1983-M-014.
  - Faculty meeting minutes
    - 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Governing Board Meetings
    - 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14 - 15)
    - 1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Reorganization
    - Statement regarding policy and organization, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Changes in organization, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Reports on Engineering at Yale, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 22 - 23)
    - Correspondence
      - 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Department appointments, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Department appointments, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Subcommittee on Basic Education, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Notes of the Washington Meeting (Transcript), 1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Budget
    - 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - 1926-1928 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Appointments, 1919-1930 (Box 4, Folder 40 - 42)
    - Correspondence on appointments, 1929-1936 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Research Budget, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Research Budget, 1946-1949 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Departmental Budget, 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1921-1924 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Construction of Mason and Dunham Labs
    - Dunham Lab
      - Wire Tire Construction, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Construction by Sargent & Co./ Shepard Electric Crane and Hoist Co., 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Bement Pond Co. and New England Engineering, 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      - Macbeth Evans Glass, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 51)
      - Lighting, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 52)
      - Lighting specifications, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Wells Construction Co., 1913-1916 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Johnson Service Co., 1913 (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - H. W. Johns Manville Co., 1913 (Box 5, Folder 56)
      - Floors, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Economy Concrete Co., 1913 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - Dreadnought Flooring Co., 1913 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - J. J. Cope Underground, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Connecticut Telephone/Electric Co., 1913 (Box 6, Folder 61)
      - The Bryant Electric Co., 1912 (Box 6, Folder 62)
      - Blueprints of switchboard, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 63)
      - Index to specifications, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 64)
      - Lecture Room, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Mason Lab
      - Preliminary notes on Mason, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Centenary
    - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Invitation lists, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 69 - 70)
    - Budget, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Yale Scientific Magazine- "Engineering Centennial" Issue, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - Centenary articles - fromYale Scientific MagazineandYale Alumni Magazine, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 74 - 76)
  - Yale Engineering Association
    - Meeting at New Haven, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 7, Folder 78 - 79)
    - Engineering at Yale pamphlet, 1921-1923 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Yearbooks, 1925-1929 (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Publicity, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Newsletters, 1919-1926 (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Safety Conference, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Engineering Questionnaires and Statistics
    - 1919 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - 1919 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - 1919 (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - 1919 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Correspondence of Professor Bozell, 1919-1920 (Box 10, Folder 90 - 95)
  - Graduate Students
    Student records are restricted until January 1, 2033 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - 1941-1942 (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - 1943 (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 11, Folder 98)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 11, Folder 104)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 11, Folder 105)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 12, Folder 109)
    - Ph.D. study in Electrical Engineering, 1943-1947 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - Ph.D. exams and solutions to problems, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - Ph.D. exam
    - Policy on Part-time Graduate Students, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - Graduate applications, 1951-1952 (Box 13, Folder 118 - 120)
    - Correspondence for Graduate Students admitted, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 121)
    - Correspondence for Graduate Students admitted, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 122)
  - Reports on Engineering Inspection Trip
    - Gorm., Elmer J.: report, 1925 (Box 13, Folder 123)
    - Goundry, E. K.: report, 1925 (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Hanford, J. B.: report, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 125)
    - Hinkley, J. W., III: report, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 126)
    - Komroff, Paul: report, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 127)
    - Komroff, Paul: report (bound), 1927 (Box 14, Folder 128)
    - Lane, John P.: report, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 129)
    - Augustine, Charles J.: report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 130)
    - Augustine, Charles J.: appendix to report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 131)
    - Brooks, Charles E.: report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - Brown, W. J.: report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 133)
    - Cook, Charles D.: report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 134)
    - Kelly, W. T., Jr.: report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 135)
    - Mallett, W. R.: report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 136)
    - Paterson, George, Jr.: report, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 137)
    - Paterson, George, Jr.: report, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 138)
    - Geers, Henry: report, 1931 (Box 16, Folder 139)
  - Class Exercises, Experiments, and Seminars
    - 1911 (Box 16, Folder 140 - 141)
    - 1912 (Box 16, Folder 142)
    - 1913 (Box 16, Folder 143 - 146)
    - 1914 (Box 17, Folder 147 - 163)
    - 1914 (Box 18, Folder 164 - 169)
    - 1914 (Box 19, Folder 170 - 171)
    - 1915 (Box 19, Folder 172 - 176)
    - 1916 (Box 20, Folder 177 - 181)
    - 1923 (Box 20, Folder 182)
    - 1924 (Box 20, Folder 183 - 185)
    - 1924 (Box 21, Folder 186 - 195)
    - 1925 (Box 21, Folder 196)
    - 1926 (Box 22, Folder 197 - 198)
    - n.d. (Box 22, Folder 199 - 201)
  - Faculty Working Sheets[salary and course information]
    Faculty working sheets are restricted until January 1, 2034 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - 1919-1926 (Box 22, Folder 202)
    - 1927-1932 (Box 23, Folder 203)
    - 1932-1933 (Box 23, Folder 204)
    - 1934-1941 (Box 23, Folder 205)
    - 1941-1947 (Box 23, Folder 206)
    - 1947-1954 (Box 23, Folder 207)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 23, Folder 208)
  - General Files
    - Student data
      - 1912-1913 (Box 24, Folder 209)
      - 1913-1920 (Box 24, Folder 210)
      - 1914 (Box 24, Folder 211)
    - Engineering historical, 1916-1946 (Box 24, Folder 212)
    - Engineering Exhibit, 1916 (Box 24, Folder 213)
    - Degrees - Radio Physics, 1919 (Box 24, Folder 214)
    - Freshman Engineering Languages, 1919 (Box 24, Folder 215 - 217)
    - Westinghouse Switchboard data, 1928 (Box 24, Folder 218 - 219)
    - Fred L. Young Papers, 1939 (Box 24, Folder 220)
    - Service Bureau, 1943 (Box 25, Folder 221)
    - Weymouth Instrument Co., 1943 (Box 25, Folder 222)
    - Draft Boards, 1943-1945 (Box 25, Folder 223)
    - Treasurer, 1943, 1947 (Box 25, Folder 224)
    - Scholarship, 1943-1944 (Box 25, Folder 225)
    - Westinghouse, 1943-1945 (Box 25, Folder 226)
    - Public Utilities Lab arrangements, 1943-1946 (Box 25, Folder 227)
    - Lecture on Heating and Cooling, 1944 (Box 25, Folder 228)
    - Speed Control, 1944 (Box 25, Folder 229)
    - Student irregularities, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 230)
    - Charles F. Kettering, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 231)
    - Kilgore Bill, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 232)
    - Navy Electronic Equipment, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 233)
    - News, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 234)
    - Phillip F. Ordung Papers, 1946 (Box 25, Folder 235)
    - Brookhaven Laboratory, 1947 (Box 25, Folder 236)
    - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, 1948 (Box 25, Folder 237)
    - Report on Physics, 1950 (Box 25, Folder 238)
    - A. G. Conrad, 1952 (Box 25, Folder 239)
    - A. G. Conrad, 1952 (Box 26, Folder 240)
    - Books by Faculty Itembers, 1956 (Box 26, Folder 241)
    - Single Phase Railway (Box 26, Folder 242)
    - Leaflets (Box 26, Folder 243)
    - References to the Works and Papers of Pliplmon Henry Dudley (Box 26, Folder 244)
  - Spring ' Inspection -Trip
    - 1952 (Box 27, Folder 245)
    - 1953 (Box 27, Folder 246)
    - 1954 (Box 27, Folder 247)
    - 1955 (Box 27, Folder 248)
    - 1956 (Box 27, Folder 249)
    - 1957 (Box 27, Folder 250)
    - 1958 (Box 27, Folder 251)
    - 1959 (Box 27, Folder 252)
    - 1960 (Box 27, Folder 253)
    - 1961 (Box 27, Folder 254)
  - Experiments and Class Excercises
    - Mechanics o f Machinery Ouizzes, 1921-1938 (Box 27, Folder 255)
    - Mechanics of Machinery Final Exams, 1922-1938 (Box 27, Folder 256)
    - Mechanisms and Kinematics Quizzes, 1943-1962 (Box 28, Folder 257)
    - Mechanisms and Kinematics Final Exams, 1943-1964 (Box 28, Folder 258)
    - Machine Design Quizzes and Exams, 1945-1950 (Box 28, Folder 259)
    - Final Exams in Accelerated Courses, 1942-1944 (Box 28, Folder 260)
  - Committee on Transportation
    - Transportation Survey (Box 29, Folder 264 - 265)
    - Various papers (Box 29, Folder 266 - 269)
    - Commentary on Railway Transportation (Box 29, Folder 270)
    - Dean S. Dudley's Papers (Box 30, Folder 271 - 274)
  - Economics 32
    - Student Papers, Grades, etc. (Box 30, Folder 275 - 276)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 31, Folder 277 - 282)
- Program of the Department of Mechanical Engineering's Christmas Party, 1925; Accession 2003-A-098
  The materials are open for research.
  - Program of the Department of Mechanical Engineering's Christmas Party, 1925 (Box 1)
- Board of Permanent Officers records, 1928-1963; Accession 2018-A-035
  Includes the founding documents for the School of Engineering
  - 1928-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1938-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1947-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)